快點 能用的水都用上
Come on! Let's use all the water we have!
快點...用床單撲滅火
Hurry up! Hurry up! Use sheets to put out the fire.
把這些棚屋拆掉 我們需要清出一條防火道
Tear down these huts. We need to make a firebreak.
我討厭這些火 你想要殺了我 來呀
I hate these fires. You want to kill me? Come on!
什么起火了
What's burning?
是薩嘎爾瓦達 林之前住的地方
It's Sagar Wada. It's where Lin was staying.
你說他已經離開了
You said yourself he's gone.
我好冷
I'm cold.
好的 傷口要保持干凈 明白嗎
All right. You have to keep this clean. You understand?
明白 好的
Understand. Okay.
好的 很不錯
All right. Good man.
林先生 愿和平與你同在
Salaam alaikum, Mr. Lin.
愿和平與你同在
Wa alaikumu assalam.
我是卡西姆阿里 這里的村長
I'm Qasim Ali, headman here.
帕拉布和我說了很多你的事
Prabhu has told me all about you.
謝謝你 林先生
Thank you, Mr. Lin.
多謝你的幫助
Thank you for what you are doing.
如果有更好的物資 我就能做更多事
Well, I could do more with better supplies.
如果你能把所能找到的給我...
If you get me whatever you have--
這里有些人需要住院 藥物 靜脈注射
Some of these people need hospital, drugs, IVs.
是 但這里是弄不到那些東西的
Yes, but none of these things will be coming here.
我們有的都已經給你了
You already have what we have, huh?
帕瓦蒂
Parvati?
有人能看看拉克什米嗎
Can someone take a look at Lakshmi?
拉克什米 發生什么了
What happened? What happened, Lakshmi?
林 快過來
Lin, come here!
好的 把她扶到這邊
Okay, bring her here.
再給我一張桌子 把她放平
I need another table, to lie her down.
慢一點 輕一點...
Slowly. Easy, easy.
好的 你沒事 對 你很好
Okay. You're all right. No, you're okay.
你沒事的...慢慢來
You're all right. Easy. You're all right.
問問她呼吸是否有困難
Ask her if she's having trouble breathing.
她需要去醫院才能移除這金屬
She needs a hospital to take out that metal.
什么 你做不到嗎  -對 不可能的
What, you can't do this? -No. No way.
我認為那金屬刺穿了她的肺部
I think it's punctured her lung.
媽媽 -拉維
Mom. -Ravi!
不...出來了
No. No, no, no! It came out.
拉維 -媽媽
Ravi! -Mom!
帕拉布 用手按住 好嗎
Prabhu! Put your hands on there, all right?
緊緊地按壓
Solid pressure.
手拿開...
Move your hands. Move your hands!
你抱著她 可以嗎  -好的
I need you to hold her. All right? -Okay.
別讓她移動 -好的
Don't let her move. -Okay.
告訴她這能幫助她呼吸
Tell her this is gonna help her breathe.
別碰她
Don't touch her!
別碰我媽媽
Get away from my mother!
卡西姆 太吵了 我聽不見
Qasim, I need to be able to hear.
拉維 別這樣 他是想救她
Ravi, stop! He's trying to help her.
拉維 -可以嗎
Ravi. -That good?
拉維... -媽媽
Ravi. Ravi. -Mom!
拉維
Ravi.
該死的 見鬼
Shit. Fuck.
怎么了  -她必須立即看醫生
What happened? -She needs a doctor now.
讓開...
Move! Move!
帕拉布 幫我將她抬起來
Prabhu, help me lift her.
數到三 一 二 三
On three. One, two, three.
媽媽 -林先生 你要帶她去哪
Mom. -Mr. Lin, where are you taking her?
她需要見醫生 否則很快就會死去
She needs a doctor, or she's gonna die quickly.
那就讓她死在所愛之人的環繞下吧
Then let her die surrounded by the people she loves.
我希望她能在所愛之人的陪伴下生活
I want her to live with the people she loves,
不是在陪伴下死去 帕拉布
not die with them. Prabhu?
這是不對的 -數到三 一 二 三
This is wrong. -On three. One, two, three.
拉維... -拉克什米 沒事
Ravi. Ravi. -Lakshmi, it's okay.
我們要帶你去看醫生 -快...
We're taking you to the doctor. -Go, go, go!
拉維...
Ravi. Ravi! Ravi.
別擔心 拉維 他們在救你的母親
Don't worry, Ravi. They're helping your mother.
林
Lin.
林 聽我說
Lin, listen!
帕拉布 她不能死 不能因我而死
She's not dying, Prabhu. Not because of me.
嘿 幫幫我們
Hey! We need help!
嘿 停車 嘿
Hey! Stop! Hey!
帕拉布... -這里有位女人生命垂危
Prabhu, Prabhu. -We got a dying woman here!
帕拉布...
Prabhu. Prabhu.
嘿...停下
Hey. Hey, stop!
林 停下 夠了
Lin, stop! Enough!
她說了什么
What did she say?
那不重要了
It does not matter.
我想知道
I want to know.
她想見拉維
She asked for Ravi.
他們很快就會回來
They'll be back soon.
有多少個棚屋被燒毀了
How many huts have burned?
30個 包括我的
Thirty. Mine included.
媽媽
Mom!
我去拿點食物和奶茶 好嗎
I will go get some food and chai, okay?
我不餓
I'm not hungry.
林
Lin.
你已經盡力做到最好 我清楚 所以你可以...
You were trying to do the best thing. I know this. So you can--
這是我的錯
This was my fault.
帕拉布 要不是我在這里 根本就不會有這場火
Prabhu, if I hadn't been here, this fire would've never happened--
林 拜托...
Lin, please. Please.
這里發生火災并不奇怪
Fires, they happen here.
你認為拉克什米的死不讓我難過嗎
You think I'm not hating Lakshmi is gone, huh?
這一次我們已經算幸運
This time, we are lucky.
去年發生過一場更大的火災 貧民區被燒毀的地方更多
Last year, there was much bigger fire, much more of the jhopadpatti was burned.
20多個人死去
More than 20 died.
我帶點食物回來 好嗎
I will bring food, okay?
放下...該死...
Drop the-- Fuck. Fuck.
放下剪貼板 舉起雙手
Drop the clipboard and put your hands up.
你快啊
Get the fuck on.
別碰任何警報鍵 知道嗎
Don't touch any fucking alarm buttons, all right?
你們幾位女士 能把這些袋子裝滿嗎
Could you ladies fill these bags up, please?
全都有保險的 真的不用擔心
It's all insured. It's really not worth worrying about.
照他說的做吧
Just do what he says.
求你了 勞拉 -好的...
Please... Laura. -Okay, okay, okay.
懶惰的混蛋 為什么不找個工作
Why don't you get a job, you lazy bastards?
嘿 不好意思 這就是我們的工作 肥豬
Hey! Excuse me, this is our job, you fat ass.
別擋我們的道 懂嗎
Don't get in the way of us doing it, all right?
來吧 親愛的 別擔心 你只需要把袋子裝滿
Come on, love. It's all good. You just need to fill the bag.
看不出來她很害怕嗎
Can't you see she's terrified?
把袋子裝滿
Just fill the bag!
讓一讓...
Out of the way! Out of the way! Move! Move!
看路
Watch it.
抱歉 哥們 是我的錯
Sorry, mate. My fault.
嘿 放開我
Hey. Get off me.
把槍放下
Drop the bloody gun.
放開我 混蛋 放下槍
Get off me! Bastard. Drop the gun!
別碰我
Get the fuck off me.
把槍放下 快放下... -好...
Drop the gun! Drop it! Drop it! -Okay. Okay. Okay!
你干了什么
What did you do?
走吧
Move.
戴爾
Dale.
戴爾 快走
Dale, fucking move.
快點 走吧
Now. Come on.
戴爾
Dale.
快叫救護車
Somebody, call an ambulance.
好的 嘿...保持清醒 嘿
Okay. Hey, hey. Stay with me. Hey.
你不會有事的 伙計 你沒事的
You're all right, mate. You're all right.
保持清醒
Stay with me.
離他遠點
Get away from him!
愿和平與你同在 瓦利德拜
Salaam alaikum, Walidbhai.
愿和平與你同在 卡德爾拜
Alaikumu assalam, Khaderbhai.
這個地方選得有意思
Interesting choice of location.
一想到過去的好日子里 多少人曾在這謀生 就感到難過啊
Sad to think how many men once earned a living here in better days.
伙計 一切事物都有使用期限 對吧
Arre, everything has its use-by date, huh?
一切人也是
And everyone.
你想聊聊 我們可以在這聊
Now, you wanted to talk. This is where we can do it.
魯祖阿德卡死了
Rujul Aadekar is dead.
如果我是你 我也會做同樣的事
Had I been in your shoes, I would have done exactly the same.
所有公司都處于和平狀態
All the companies are at peace.
我們的人沒有在街上互相殺戮和開槍
Our men are not killing and shooting each other in the streets,
每個人都心滿意足
and everyone is satisfied.
公司之間很和平是因為 經營者都是些疲憊的老人
The companies are at peace because they're run by tired, old men
安于現狀
who've settled for the status quo.
除了你的
Except yours?
除了我的
Except mine.
魯祖生前認為你軟弱 對嗎
Rujul, he believed you are weak, huh?
知道何為正確不意味著一個人軟弱
Certainty of what is right does not make anyone weak,
否則經營克拉巴護照市場的 會是你 而不是我
or you'd still be running the passport market in Colaba, not me.
瓦利德 是因為這個嗎
Is that what this is, Walid?
因為自尊心受傷 你想掀起戰爭
You want to start a war over your hurt pride?
我不打算掀起任何東西 伙計 這只關乎生意
I'm not starting anything. This is business, yaar.
薩嘎爾瓦達價值連城 所以我不過是向魯祖出了更高的價
Sagar Wada is worth a fortune. So, I simply made Rujul a better offer.
我是不會失去薩嘎爾瓦達的
I am not going to lose Sagar Wada.
這算是威脅嗎
Is that a threat?
只是簡單陳述事實
A simple statement of fact.
對你來說是事實而已吧 大叔
For you maybe, chachu, huh?
一個男人也許認為自己的老婆漂亮
You see, one man can say his wife is beautiful,
但另一個男人卻覺得她丑陋
and another only sees a pig.
要我簡單陳述事實的話 我的人手和金錢比你多
You see, I think it is a simple fact that I have more men and money than you.
我也認為女人和毒品生意才有未來
I think it is a simple fact that women and drugs are the future,
然而你選擇留在過去
and yet you choose to stay in the past.
卡德爾拜 你必須給人們他們想要的東西
You have to give the people what they want, Khaderbhai.
否則你會成為歷史
Otherwise, you are consigned to history.
也許我會在我的地盤 薩嘎爾瓦達的門前為你建一座大雕像
Maybe I'll build a big statue of you at the gates of my Sagar Wada, huh?
和你交談總是很愉快 瓦利德拜
Always a pleasure talking with you, Walidbhai.
你醒了 太好了 跟我來 有個東西你必須看看 老大
You're awake? Good. Come. Something you gotta see, boss.
好的 稍等片刻
All right. Just give me a minute.
快點啊 哥們
Come, na.
嗨
Hey.
他們在做什么
What are they all doing?
他們是你的病人
They're your patients.
你在說什么呢
What are you talking about?
他們都知道你昨晚治療居民的事
They all know about the doctoring you did last night,
所以現在排隊來看你
so now they wait to see you.
不...我可不是...
No. No. I'm not--
林 不會有問題的 林先生 -我不行
Lin, no-- no problem waiting, Linbaba. -I can't.
他們已經等了一個多小時了 我說你得睡覺
They're here more than one hour already. I told them you must sleep.
帕拉布
Prabhu.
就算你沒來 他們也會繼續等的
Even if you were not here, they would still be waiting
只是白等一場
but waiting for nothing only.
那會讓他們失去希望
And that kills the heart.
但是等待有所回報 那就不同了 對吧
But waiting for something, that is different, na?
我不能這么做 聽著 我都不算醫生
I can't do that. Look, I'm not even a doctor.
糟糕的醫生總比沒醫生好
Even bad doctor better than no doctor.
我不是說你糟糕 意思是即使你糟糕也沒事
I'm not saying you are bad, only that if you were, it would be okay.
林 拜托了
Lin, please.
帕拉布 -拉克什米原本就無法生還的
Prabhu. -Lakshmi was going to die anyway.
我們會為她悼念
And we will grieve her.
但有時生活就是這樣
But that is how it is sometimes.
帕拉布 你好嗎  -好
How are you, Prabhu? -Okay.
林先生
Mr. Lin.
聽著 關于昨晚 我想道歉 你是對的 我應該聽你的話
Look, I wanna say sorry about last night. You were right. I should have listened.
卡西姆 他會幫我們嗎
Qasim, is he going to help us?
我從沒這么想逃跑過
I wanted to run more than ever,
用卡拉的錢賦予我的第二次機會 就此離開孟買
take the second chance Karla's money had given me and get out of Bombay,
雖然我接受的幫助令這些人蒙受痛苦
despite what helping me had done to these people.
會很好的 相信我
It will be good, you'll see.
上帝保佑
God willing.
林先生 這筆錢不少啊
This is a lot of money to be giving away, Linbaba.
是的 我需要的東西也不少
Yeah, well, I'm gonna need a lot of things.
可你為什么要這么做
But why you do this?
我有我的原因
I've got my reasons.
來吧 收下 用這筆錢重建燒毀的屋子
Go on, take it. Use it to rebuild the homes that burned.
拜托你了
Please.
我會確保每分每毫都用在對的地方
I will make sure every paisa is well spent.
好了 再等兩分鐘 好嗎
All right! Just two more minutes. Okay?
好的
Okay.
涂抹一點這個 好吧
Put some of this on, all right?
只可能是我
It had to be me.
接受過相同培訓的人 不會因為犯罪而被迫躲在貧民區里
Another man with my training wouldn't have been forced by crime into the slum.
而罪犯不會像我一樣接受過醫療培訓
Another criminal wouldn't have had my training.
我不懂當中的幽默 我也不覺得這命運好笑在哪
I didn't get the joke, and fate didn't make me laugh.
但我知道我不能離開
But I knew I couldn't leave.
還有20個病人
We have 20 more patients.
好嗎 出來 好的
Okay? Out. Okay.
快點...
Let's go. Let's go.
嗨
Hi.
你得吃點東西
You need to eat.
早餐可真是豐盛啊
Breakfast of champions.
你有時候真幼稚
You can be such a child sometimes.
你是因為我幫你戒毒而生我氣嗎
Are you angry with me for helping you get clean?
生氣的人是你
You're the one who's angry.
總是要照顧我這點讓你這么生氣嗎
Does it piss you off so much that you have to look after me?
我希望你能照顧好自己 莉莎
I want you to look after yourself, Lisa.
但你不會的 因為你就喜歡自己孱弱無力
But you won't, because you like being powerless,
因為無論你身處哪一個宇宙 這讓你成為那里的中心
because it makes you the center of whatever universe you happen to be in.
有人照顧他人是出于愛
Some people look after you because they love you.
這又不是壞事
That's not a bad thing.
如果那人離開了呢
And what happens when they aren't there?
你不能一輩子拒絕關心某人
You can't spend your life refusing to care for anyone
只因他們可能離開
in case they leave.
莉莎 我不能和你吵 現在不行
I can't do this, Lisa. Not now.
現在的情況下 我不想和你爭執
I don't wanna fight with you, not with everything else.
對不起
I'm sorry.
你說得對 我的表現太自私 像個被寵壞的賤人
You're right. I'm being a selfish, spoiled bitch.
怎么了
What is it?
昨天我滿腦子都在想不能軟弱
Yesterday, all I could think about was not being weak.
現在我一閉眼 只看到死去的魯祖
And now, I close my eyes, and all I see is Rujul dead.
卡達爾知道
Khader knew.
他想保護我 但他做得越多
He tried to protect me, and the more he did,
我就越是堅定地想要證明自己能應對
the more I was determined to prove myself I could handle it.
卡拉 你不需要證明任何事的
You don't have to prove anything, Karla.
如果我不那么做 交易會失敗
If I don't, the deal will fall apart.
那有多糟呢
And would that be so bad?
你上次任自己放松 感到快樂 是什么時候
When is the last time you let yourself go and felt happy?
真正的快樂
Truly happy?
我們一起當廢物吧
Let's be fucked-up together.
我保證會吃一些 不對你犯渾
I promise to eat some of this and not be a royal pain in the ass,
只要你保證留在這陪我 和我一起聽唱片 像舊日一樣
if you promise to stay here with me and play records with me like old times
直到我們喝光了酒 嗑完了大麻
until we run out of booze and hash.
好的
Okay.
你需要休息 我可以讓他們明天再來
You are needing rest? I can tell them to come back tomorrow.
不 我沒事
No, I'm good.
停下 林醫生要休息一下
Stop! Dr. Lin will be taking a break now.
這是給你的謝禮 林醫生
This is a thank-you, Dr. Lin.
其實這是帕拉布的主意
Well, it was actually Prabhu's idea.
是我的主意
It was my idea.
他說服卡西姆阿里這么做 讓我用他的棚屋
He talked Qasim Ali into it and let me use his hut.
是我說服卡西姆阿里的
I talked Qasim Ali into it.
是帕拉布買來了所有這些物資
It was Prabhu who got all the supplies.
物資是我買的
I got the supplies.
帕拉布 你這么做真好
Prabhu, this was a good thing that you did.
你需要幫忙照料病人嗎
You need help with patients?
不用了 我們可以的 謝謝
No. We're good, thank you.
不過這個很好吃啊
This is great, though.
林先生 不錯吧 非常順利...
Very good, huh, Linbaba? Very slick, very smooth,
直到你讓她走 帕瓦蒂
until you sent her away. Parvati!
多謝你
Thank you, huh?
如果你想的話 吃完后 我可以把盤子送還你
If you like, I will bring back your tray when we are finished.
去奶茶店
At the chai shop.
你會在那里嗎
You'll be there?
我會在那里
I'll be there.
好啦 你們看什么呢 你們沒正事干嗎
All right, what are you staring at? Haven't you got work to do?
走吧
Let's go.
你看得有滋有味啊
You are enjoying, huh?
很美味...
Yummy, yummy.
宮殿的營運模式是預約制
The Palace operates on an appointment-only basis.
宮殿營運是因為我們允許它營運
The Palace operates because we let it.
告訴周說我們到了 去吧
Tell Zhou we're here. Go.
帕德瑪 我不是某個無助的女孩 會屈從你們的規矩
I'm not some helpless girl, Padma, that will bend to your discipline.
你必須把攜帶的武器留在這里
You will need to leave any weapons you carry here.
我不會
No, I won't.
卡德爾拜 太榮幸了 請問需要什么喝的或吃的嗎
This is an honor, Khaderbhai. Can I get you something to drink or eat?
最近我與魯祖阿德卡 進行了非常嚴肅的會面
Recently, I spent a solemn moment with Rujul Aadekar.
今晨我和瓦利德沙會面
This morning, I spent some time with Walid Shah.
現在 我來看你
And now, I've come to see you.
我不贊許你做的生意
I do not approve of your business,
但我理解這種生意必定會存在
but I understand it is a business that must exist.
所以你被允許來這里 蓬勃發展
So, you've been allowed to come here and prosper.
但是你的成功基于一個條件 就是中立
But there has been one condition to your success. Neutrality.
我犯了一個錯 卡德爾拜
I made a mistake, Khaderbhai.
我只能道歉
I can only apologize.
一開始我以為你知悉
At first, I assumed you knew of it.
但我意識到并非如此時 已經太晚了
When I realized this wasn't the case, it was too late.
正如你說 我在孟買本地的處境脆弱...
As you say, my position here in Bombay is vulnerable--
女士 你不太擅長扮演受害者
You do not play the victim well, Madame.
希望你從前當情婦和妓女時 假裝的功力更強一點
I hope you were better at faking back when you were a mistress and a whore.
正如我說的 我犯了一個錯
Like I said, I made a mistake.
但如果我要為此死去
But if I was going to die for it,
我認為你不會親自來這里動手
I don't think you would come here yourself to watch it happen.
死去的你對我毫無用處 活著的你也許有些用處
Dead, you are of no use to me. Alive, maybe I could use you.
你應明白 當我離開這地方時 我會帶上你的命
Understand that when I leave this place, I will take your life with me
作為你現在所欠債務的抵押品
as collateral against the debt that you now owe.
當我向你提出要求 你必須滿足
And when I ask something of you, you will do it,
否則這地方會成為你的葬身殿
or this place will burn as your funeral pyre.
你是怎么知道的
How did you know?
是卡拉薩蘭恩說的
Was it Karla Saaranen?
誰
Who?
我沒聽過這名字
I do not know that name.
魯祖是我的人
Rujul belonged to me.
我對他的了解勝過他對自己的了解
I knew him better than he knew himself.
所以我派人跟蹤他 他去過哪里 做了什么 見了誰
So I had him followed, where he went, what he did, who he saw.
他沒想到這一點是他愚蠢
He was stupid to think otherwise.
而他的愚蠢讓他送命
It was his stupidity that got him killed.
希望你并不愚蠢 女士
I hope you're not stupid, Madame.
林先生 我們要為拉克什米的葬禮造柴堆
Linbaba, we are now going to build the pyre for Lakshmi's funeral
歡迎你一起來
if you want to come.
對不起 強尼 我沒資格去
I'm sorry, Johnny. I got no right to be there.
帕拉布說你責怪自己
Prabhu told me you blame yourself.
帕拉布話太多了
Prabhu talks too much.
是
Yeah.
卡德爾拜今天饒了你一命 這么做明智嗎
Khaderbhai gave you your life today. Is this wise?
我的命不由任何人賜予或拿走
My life isn't any man's to give or take.
我和他們一樣了解他們的生意
I know their business as well as them.
這些“大哥”...去他們的
All these bhais... Fuck them.
也許是時候讓位給“大姐”了 帕德瑪
Maybe it's time for the behains, Padma.
我們之間有協定
We had a deal, you and I.
如果你說的是莉莎 我遵從了協定
If you're talking about Lisa, I kept my part of it.
莉莎離開了
Lisa is gone.
我不認為那是我的錯
I don't see how that is my fault.
毛里齊奧 那你在怕什么
Then why are you scared, Maurizio?
我不怕
I am not.
我認為你怕
I think you are.
我認為只有這種時候 男人和女人才能真正一樣
I think maybe it's the only time when men and women can truly be the same,
當他們無權無勢 害怕至極時
when they're powerless and terrified.
可是女人被迫擁有這種感受的時刻 比男人多得多
But women are forced to feel it so much more than men.
往往是被男人逼迫
By men, usually.
為什么叫我來這里
Why am I here?
你想得到我的原諒 有一個辦法
There is a way for you to earn my forgiveness.
請說
I'm listening.
我想要你在克拉巴幫我賣海洛因
I want you to sell brown sugar for me in Colaba.
克拉巴是卡德爾拜的地盤
Colaba is Khaderbhai's territory.
但他不在那里賣海洛因
But he doesn't sell heroin there.
其他人也沒有
Neither does anyone else.
我對他并沒有忠誠 你呢
I owe him no loyalty. Do you?
我
Me?
我對任何人都沒有忠誠
I owe loyalty to no one.
至少這是大實話
Which is honest, at least.
我的條件很簡單
My terms are simple.
不得提我的名字 你抽二成利潤
My name is never mentioned. You keep 20% of the profit.
四成 風險全由我承擔
Forty. I'm taking all of the risk.
我不是在和你磋商
I'm not negotiating with you.
大概有多少
How much are we talking about?
你能賣多少 我就有多少阿富汗海洛因
I have access to as much Afghan dope as you can sell.
好的 說定了
Okay then. You have a deal.
那你就不需要害怕任何事了
Then you have nothing to fear.
林先生
Mr. Lin?
我叫阿卜杜拉塔哈利
My name's Abdullah Taheri.
有個人想見你
I have someone who wants to meet you.
好的 誰
Okay. Who is it?
請
Please.
林賽福特先生
Mr. Lindsay Ford?
叫我林就好
Just "Lin" works.
見到你很高興 久仰大名
I'm pleased to meet you. I've heard good things.
在孟買這里聽到關于外國人的好話 總是令人開心
It's always nice to hear good things about foreigners here in Bombay.
也許你也聽過我 我是阿布戴爾卡達爾可汗
You might have heard of me also. My name is Abdel Khader Khan.
你現在是棚屋區醫生了
So, you are the doctor in the hutments now.
這個 我...距離醫生還遠著呢
Well, I'm-- I'm a long way from being a doctor.
也許正是因此你才這么出色
Well, maybe that is why you are doing so well.
醫生不會主動來貧民區
Doctors do not go into the jhopadpatti willingly.
我們可以說服人不做壞事
We can compel men not to be bad,
但我們無法說服他們做好事 你不覺得嗎
but we cannot compel them to do good, don't you find?
我從沒思考過這點
I never really thought about it.
不知道什么東西能說服你
I wonder what compels you.
有什么能幫你的嗎
Is there something I can do for you?
我還不知道
I don't know yet.
所以我才來這里
That is why I am here,
邀請你和我的朋友阿卜杜拉聊聊
to invite you to spend some time with me and my friend Abdullah.
好吧 我無意冒犯 但是我就直說了
All right. I mean no offense, but I'm just gonna say this.
你的名聲挺嚇人的
You have a fairly scary reputation.
所以你突然這樣出現 應該不難理解我有點緊張
So you just turning up like this, you can see why I might be a bit nervous
不太想坐上你車的后座 讓你載我走
about jumping in the back of your car and letting you drive me away.
我向你保證 今晚你不會受到任何傷害
I give you my word. No harm will come to you this night.
我有選擇嗎
Do I have a choice?
你永遠都有選擇
You always have a choice.
最終 我認為選擇是我們唯一擁有的東西
In the end, I think that is all we have.
好吧
Okay.
宵禁就像不存在一樣
So much for curfew.
當局知道
The authorities know
大城市的文明人需要聚會和謀生的地方
that civilized people in large cities need places to gather and hunt.
所以某些地方可以行賄 秩序得以被保留
So certain establishments are permitted to pay a bribe, and order is preserved.
明面上法律依然有效 但不會執行
Officially, the law remains. It's just not enforced.
誰決定哪些法律要執行 哪些法律不執行呢
Who gets to decide which laws get enforced and which ones don't?
有人曾說腐敗作為管治系統的一部分 最糟糕的一點在于
Someone once said the worst thing about corruption as a system of governance
它的效果太好了
is that it works so well.
拉米什
Ramesh!
你父親可好
How is your father?
他很好 卡德爾拜 謝謝
He is well, Khaderbhai. Thank you.
但我遇到了麻煩
But I am having a problem.
告訴我
Tell me.
先生 是關于我的房東
Bhai, it's about my landlord.
他已經要求租金漲一倍
He is demanding double rent already.
他想驅逐我們 不只是我 還有樓里的所有家庭
He wants to evict us, not just me, but all the families in my building.
他有打手 他的打手把我們打得很慘
He has goondas, and his goondas beat us badly.
甚至包括我的父親
Even my own father.
那么你父親并不好
Then he is not well.
是的 先生 他的自尊心太強 不愿向你求助
No, sir. He is too proud to ask you for help
不想打擾你
and doesn't want to disturb your peace.
可是我...
But I...
你是個好兒子
You're a good son.
我們不會做任何傷害他自尊心的事
We won't do anything to hurt his pride.
也毋須和你父親提及這次談話
And there will be no need to speak to your father about this
直到這個麻煩解決 愿上帝保佑
until the problem is solved, inshallah.
謝謝你... -好的 是...
Thank you, thank-- -Okay, okay. Yes, yes, yes.
你聽懂了多少
How much did you understand?
沒多少 關于他家和他父親什么的
Not much. Something about his home and his father.
他們的房東想趕走他們
Their landlord wants them out of their place.
必要時會動粗
By force, if necessary.
所以你去威脅那個威脅他們的人
So you threaten the man who threatens them?
你贊同嗎
Do you approve?
我覺得你并不需要我的贊同
I don't think you need my approval.
你是阿布戴爾卡達爾可汗
You're Abdel Khader Khan.
只因為我可以輕易做某事 不意味著我應該這么做
Just because I can easily do something doesn't always mean I should.
如果換做是你 你覺得應該這樣做嗎
Humor me. If it were you?
我覺得如果我喜歡拉米什 而這個房東的做法很過分
I think if I liked Ramesh and this landlord was out of line,
那我會盡我所能幫助他
then I'd do what I could for him.
就算那可能違法
Even if it meant acting against the law?
誰決定哪些法律要執行 哪些法律不執行呢
Who gets to choose which laws get enforced and which ones don't?
最終 無論是哪條法律 無論是誰來選擇
In the end, regardless of laws or who chooses,
我們每一個人 每個宇宙 每個星系中的每個原子
each one of us, every atom in every galaxy in every universe,
都會向上帝靠近
is moving towards God.
我不信上帝
I don't believe in God.
那么我們能聊的就更多了 你和我
Then we have much more to talk about, you and I.
走 我們帶他去俱樂部
Let's go. We will take him to the club.
你說了會陪我 -不 我只是沒說不會陪
You said you'd stay with me. -No. I just didn't say I wouldn't.
你的協定
Your deal.
莉莎 我已經走到這一步 我沒有選擇
I've come too far, Lisa. I don't have a choice.
可不能讓卡達爾可汗先生失望
Can't disappoint Mr. Khader Khan.
留下 求你了
Stay. Please.
為了我們倆
For both of us.
我能看出這給你帶來的影響 你也知道
I can see what this is doing to you. You know it too.
你只是不愿承認
You just won't admit it.
選擇我 陪著我
Choose me. Stay with me.
因為這才是最重要的
Because this matters the most.
我很在乎你 你清楚的
I care about you. You know that.
但你還是要選他
But you're choosing him anyway.
這家俱樂部有孟買最棒的加扎勒歌手
This club has the best ghazel singers in Bombay.
什么是加扎勒
What are ghazels?
愛之曲 給上帝的愛之曲
Love songs. Love songs to God.
無論你怎么想 信上帝這件事并不存在
No matter what you might think, there is no believing in God.
我們認識上帝 或不認識 只有這兩種
We either know him or we do not.
我不認識上帝 但我覺得 他的存在不太可能
Well, I don't know God, but I think he's pretty much impossible.
上帝的存在不太可能正是他存在的證據
The fact that God is impossible is proof he exists.
所以是不是所有可能的事物都不存在呢
So does that mean that all possible things don't exist?
很高興你理解我的意思
I'm delighted you understand.
我真的不理解
I really don't.
我的朋友 你有麻煩了
You're in trouble now, my friend.
沒有任何事物是我們所看到的樣子 我們的眼睛是騙子
Nothing exists as we see it. Our eyes are liars.
一切看上去真實的東西都屬于某種幻象
Everything that seems real is part of the illusion.
你 我 這個房間
You, me, this room.
那么如果一切都是幻象 那我們怎么知道做什么 如何生活
So if everything's an illusion, how do we know what to do, how to live?
我們說謊
We lie.
頭腦清醒的人不過是比 頭腦不清醒的人更擅長說謊罷了
The sane man is simply a better liar than the insane man.
你的眼睛會說謊
Your eyes lie.
你以為自己知道的事情 讓你認為并非如此 那其實這是真的
What you think you know tells you this is not so, but it's true.
我們更喜歡謊言 因為那樣更簡單
We prefer the lie because it's easier.
那要如何保持清醒
That's how we stay sane?
我沒有結婚 我沒有兒子
I am not married, and I have no sons.
但如果我告訴你 我清楚地看到你是我的兒子
But if I tell you that I see it clearly that you are my son,
阿卜杜拉是你的哥哥 我是你的父親
Abdullah is your brother, I am your father,
你會認為這不可能
you will think that is impossible.
你會抗拒 你確實如此 我看得出
You will resist it. You do. I see it.
你寧肯相信我們都是陌生人這個謊言
You prefer to believe the lie that we are all strangers,
相信我們之間沒有關連
and there is no connection between us.
我有父親
I have a father.
我不了解你 你不了解我
And I don't know you. You don't know me.
也許我了解
I think maybe I do.
林先生 你會對自己說哪些謊言
What do you lie to yourself about, Mr. Lin?
我不會 我已經不再那樣做了
I don't. I'm finished with that.
我知道自己是誰 做了什么 欠了什么
I know what I am, what I've done, what I owe.
我決定喜歡林這個人
你覺得這音樂如何
How did you like the music?
棒極了 從沒聽過這樣的音樂
It's incredible. I never heard anything like it before.
能問你一件事嗎
Can I ask you something?
今晚的所有這些...你為什么帶我來這里
All this, tonight... Why'd you bring me here?
你想在我這里得到什么
What do you want from me?
你在這里做什么
What are you doing here?
聽音樂 喝茶
Listening, drinking tea,
學習我所知道的世界是一種幻象這件事
learning that the world as I know it is an illusion.
我嗑嗨了
I'm pretty stoned.
你本應離開孟買的
You were meant to leave Bombay.
林先生 你的這位朋友是
Who is your friend, Mr. Lin?
這是卡拉薩蘭恩
This is Karla Saaranen.
我們是朋友嗎
Are we friends?
不知道
I don't know.
這么說吧 到目前我在孟買的日子里 卡拉是重要而關鍵的一部分
Let's just say Karla has had a full and central part of my life in Bombay so far.
無論是真是假
Real or not.
我覺得她是真的
I think she's real.
事實上
In fact,
卡拉證明了我是對的
Karla proves that I'm right.
如果我想象出了她 她對我的態度應該好得多
If I invented her, she would be a lot nicer to me.
卡拉 這位是阿卜杜拉塔哈利
Karla, allow me to introduce Abdullah Taheri,
他似乎是我沒有血緣關系的兄弟
my brother from another mother, apparently,
我的新相識阿布戴爾卡達爾可汗先生 讓我們兩兄弟再聚首
recently reunited by my newest acquaintance, Mr. Abdel Khader Khan.
你大概聽過他的大名 -當然
You've probably heard of him. -Of course.
薩拉恩女士 幸會
It's a pleasure to meet you, Ms. Saaranen.
彼此彼此 你們是怎么認識的
Likewise. How do you all come to know each other?
命運使然
Fate saw fit to throw us together.
還真有趣
Funny how that happens.
是的 “處于苦難中的人不擇伙伴”
Yeah, well, "Misery acquaints a man with strange bedfellows."
怪物是誰
Who's the monster?
什么意思
What do you mean?
這句話是一個和怪物同床的人說的
That line is spoken by a man who lies down with a monster.
薩蘭恩女士對莎士比亞很了解
Ms. Saaranen knows her Shakespeare.
有人曾告訴我
Someone once told me
人生中的所有問題和大部分答案
that all the questions and most of the answers in life
都可以在莎士比亞里找到
can be found in Shakespeare.
要加入我們嗎
Would you like to join us?
不行 我還有客人要招待
I can't. I've got guests of my own.
我們要談生意 我應該回去了
We have business to conclude. I should get back to them.
祝你的生意順利
Good luck with your business.
愿上帝保佑
Inshallah.
祝你們今晚愉快 先生們
Enjoy the rest of your evening, gentlemen.
林 今晚很愉快
It has been a pleasure, Lin.
這是某種考驗嗎
Was this some kind of test?
你為什么在薩嘎爾瓦達幫忙
Why do you help in Sagar Wada?
他們需要
They needed it.
那算是某種高尚舉動
An act of nobility then?
不 高尚這個詞用不到我身上 這我可以打包票
Nah, there's nothing noble about me. You can trust me on that.
人沒有好壞之分
There are no good men or bad men.
是他們做的事或不愿做的事 定義了他們的好壞
It is what they do, or refuse to do, that makes them good or evil.
這個地方對我的意義重大
This place means a great deal to me.
可汗先生 多謝你今晚的招待
Thank you for tonight, Mr. Khan.
請叫我卡德爾拜
Please, call me Khaderbhai.
卡德爾拜
Khaderbhai.
發音還算標準
Close enough.
也許是命運 讓我和這兩個人相遇 父親和兄弟
Maybe fate brought me together with these men, father and brother.
但那之后發生的一切都是我自己的選擇
But everything that came after was down to my own choices,
正如卡達爾說的
just like Khader had said.
你殺了她 你殺了我的母親
You took her away. You took my mother away.
她是我的全部
She was all I had.
是
Yeah.
雖然是無心之失 但的確如此
I didn't mean to, but I did.
拉維 我受夠了永遠做錯事
I'm tired, Ravi, of getting it so fucking wrong all the time.
你要用這個嗎
Are you gonna use that?
拉維
Ravi!
拉維 你在做什么
What are you doing, Ravi?
拉維 孩子
Ravi, my son...
你母親已經離世
Your mother is gone.
這么做 你也會毀了自己的一輩子
Do this, and you'll lose yourself forever also.
你明白嗎
Understand?
這孩子不應該
This child does not deserve
因為殺了你而背負良心的重擔 林先生
to carry your murder on his conscience, Mr. Lin.
你不懂這一點說明你是個自私的傻瓜
And you are a selfish fool for not knowing better.
去我的棚屋 你和我家人一起生活吧
Go to my hut. You will stay with my family now.
不 卡西姆叔叔 拜托 我不傷他 但...
No. Uncle Qasim, please. I won't hurt him, but...
拉維 聽我的話
Ravi. Do as I say.
去吧
Go.
你對他說了什么
What did you say to him?
他現在和我家人一起生活
That he will stay with my family now.
拉克什米的棚屋屬于你了 林先生
Lakshmi's hut will now be yours, Mr. Lin.
這里的人需要你的幫助時 就會來這里找你
When people here need your help, this is where they will find you.
這不是我給你的禮物
This is not a gift I'm giving you.
是
Yeah.
(改編自格里高利大衛羅伯茨的 小說《Shantaram》)
字幕翻譯:易晗